Hello everybody.
مرحباً جميعاً
I'm Daniel Kane.
أنا دانيال كين.
Welcome to the data structures and algorithms specialization.
مرحباً بكم في تخصص هياكل البيانات والخوارزميات.
For this very first lecture, we're going to start at the very beginning and
في هذه المحاضره الأولي, سوف نبدأ من البدايه و
talk about why do you need to study algorithms in the first place.
نتحدث عن لماذا تحتاج إلي دراسة الخوارزميات في الأساس.
So the basic goal in this lecture is to sort of talk about what are the sorts
لذا الهدف الأساسي من هذه المحاضره هو بشكل ما الحديث عن أنواع
of problems that we're going to be discussing in this algorithms class and
المشاكل التي سوف نناقشها في هذا الدرس و
why they're important.
لماذا هي مهمه.
And in the context of doing this, we're also going to discuss some problems that
وفي سياق ذلك، سوف نقوم أيضا بمناقشه بعض المشاكل التي
you might run into when writing computer programs that might not
قد تكون واجهتك وانت تكتب برامج الكمبيوتر التي قد لا
actually require sophisticated techniques that we'll be discussing in this course.
قد لا تكون بحاجه فعلا إلي تقنيات متطوره كالتي سوف يتم مناقشتها في هذا المساق.
And on the other hand,
وعلي الجانب الأخر،
we'll discuss some other sorts of problems that you might want to solve that
سوف نناقش أنواع أخري من المشاكل التي قد ترغب في حلها والتي
go beyond the sort of material that we will be talking about here.
تتخطي هذا النوع من المواد التي سوف نتحدث عنها عنا.
So, to begin with, suppose that you're writing a computer program.
لذا، في البدايه، لنفترض أنك تكتب أحد البرامج.
There are a lot of tasks that you might want to perform
هناك الكثير من المهام التي قد ترغب في القيام بها
that you don't really need to think about very hard.
والتي لا تحتاج حقاً للتفكير فيها بجدِّ.
These are things like displaying a given text on the screen, or copying
هذه المهام مثل عرض نص معين علي الشاشه، أو نسخ
a file from one location to another, or searching a file for a given word.
ملف من مكان إلي أخر، أو البحث في ملف عن كلمه معينه.
Each of these algorithms has essentially a linear scan.
وكل من هذه المسائل تتميز بآلية مسح خطية
You go through every word in the file, one at a time and
حيث تقوم بمسح كل كلمة في الملف كلمةٌ تلو الأخرى
you do the appropriate thing.
وتقوم بعدها بما يلزم
And for each of these problems there's essentially a linear scan
ولكل هذه المسائل هنالك آلية مسح خطية
that you really can't do much better than.
حيث لا يمكنك القيام بما هو أفضل من ذلك
In order to do whatever task it is you're doing,
ﻷجل أن تقوم بأي مهمة تريد القيام بها
you have to go through all the data one at a time and process it appropriately.
يجب أن تقوم بالمرور على كل البيانات واحداً تلو الأخر وتعالجها بشكل مناسب
And so when you do more or
وهكذا عندما تقوم بالأمر
less the obvious thing, you have a program that works.
البديهي فستحصل على برنامج يعمل بشكل صحيح
It solves the problem that you need.
فهو يحل المشكلة التي تريد حلها
And it does so approximately as efficiently as you could expect.
و تقريباً يقوم بهذا بالكفاءة التي تتوقعها من حل خطي
So for these sorts of problems you might not have to think very hard
ولهذا النوع من المسائل ربما لا يتوجب عليك التفكير كثيرا
about what algorithm you are using.
في أي خوارزمية تستخدم
On the other hand, there are some other problems, actual algorithms problems,
من ناحية أخرى، فهناك الكثير من المسائل ، مسائل خوارزمية حقيقية
where it's not so clear what it is you need to do.
غير واضح فيها مالمطلوب عمله
For example, you might be given a map and
على سبيل المثال ، ربما يتم اعطاؤك خريطة
need to find the shortest path between two locations on this map.
و المطلوب ايجا اقصر طريق بين موقعين على الخريطة
Or you might be given, you might be trying to find the best
او ربما يطلب منك  ان تحاول ايجاد أفضل
pairing between students and dorm rooms given some sort of list of preferences, or
ربط بين الطلاب وغرفهم الجامعية  بناء على قائمة مفروزة من الخيارات
you might be trying to measure the similarity of two different documents.
أو ربما تحاول تحديد كمية التشابه بين مستندين مختلفين
Now, for these problems it's a lot more complicated,
الان لهذا النوع من المسائل   يكون الخوارزمية معقدة جدا
it's not immediately clear how to solve these problems.
من غير الواضح كيف يمكن حل المسالة مباشرة
And even when you do come up with solutions,
حتى لو استطعت الوصول الى الحل
often the simple solutions to these problems are going to be far too slow.
فغالبا ان الحل البسيط لهذه المسائل  ، سيكون تنفيذه بطيئا جدا
You could end up with some simple algorithm,
من الممكن ان تجد خوارزمية بسيطة
you could try all possible pairings between people and dorm rooms and
فمن الممكن ان تجد جميع احتمالات الربط بين الطلاب وغرفهم الجامعية
return the one that optimizes some function that you're trying to deal with.
وايجاد الرابط الذي يطور  الدالة التي تتعامل معها
On the other hand, if you did that, it would probably take a very, very,
في كل حال ، اذا قمت بذلك  فانه سيستهلك وقتا طويلا جدا جدا
very long time.
لتنفيذ هذه العملية على الكمبيوتر
And you might not have enough time to wait, and so
وربما لايكون عندك متسع من الوقت
you might need to do something better.
و ربما تحتاج ان تفعل شيئا افضل
And then even once you have a reasonably efficient algorithm for
وحتى لو استطعت ايجاد خوارزمية فعالة الى حد ما
these problems, there's often a lot of room for further optimization.
فالغالب انك لاتزال تستطيع ان تطوره وتحسنه
Improve things so that things run in an hour rather than a day.
وبذلك تستطيع تنفيذ الخوارزمية في ساعة بدلا من يوم كامل
Or a minute rather than an hour.
او دقيقة  خير من ساعة
Or a second rather than a minute.
او ثانية خير من دقيقة
And all of these improvements will have a large effect
كل هذه التحسينات سينعكس أثرها
on how useful this program you've written is.
على أهمية البرنامج الذي كتبته
Now, on the other hand,
الان ، بطريقة أخرى
there are some things that you might want to try and do with your computer that
هناك بعض الاشياء التي تريد ان تجربها وتستخدمها على جهازك
go a little bit beyond the sort of things we're discussing in this course.
والتي ربما تكون خارج حدود الأشياء التي سنناقشها في هذه المادة
We might want to call these Artificial Intelligence Problems.
ربما تحاول مسائل الذكاء الاصطناعي
And these are problems where it's sort of
وهذا النوع من المسائل
hard to clearly state what it is that you're trying to do.
يكون تحديد المطلوب منها صعبا
An example of this might be, to try and write a computer program
احد الامثلة  ان تكتب برنامجا
to understand natural language.
لفهم لغات البشر
That is, write a program where I can type something in, some English sentence,
بمعنى ان تكتب برنامجا    ،  اذا كتبت بالانجليزية مثلا
asking it, you know, what's the price of milk at the local food store today?
كم سعر الحليب في المتجر اليوم
And you want the computer to then take this sentence that I wrote, and
وتريد من الكبيوتر ان يفهم هذه الجملة
figure out what it means, figure out some way to parse it.
ويقوم بتحليلها
And then do an appropriate lookup and return a useful answer to me.
وبعد ذلك يقوم بقليل من البحث    وارجاع الاجابة للمستخدم
And the problem with doing this isn't so much that anything involved here is
الاشكالية في هذا النوع من المسائل  ليس صعوبة تنفيذها
actually difficult to perform, but the problem is that fundamentally we
بل الصعوبة تكمن
don't really understand what it means to interpret an English sentence.
في عدم قدرتنا  على فهم الطريقة التي تفسر بها  الجمل الانجليزية
Now, I mean we can all speak English, hopefully, if you're listening to this
طبعا نحن نتكلم اللغة الانجليزية
lecture, but we don't sort of really fundamentally understand what it means.
ولكن هذا لايعني اننا حقيقة نفهم الطريقة التي  تفسر بها اللغة
It's hard to put it into precise enough language
من الصعوبة  تفسير لغة  بطريقة دقيقة وكاملة
that you can actually write a computer program to do that.
للدرجة  اننا نريد برنامجا  يصنع ذلك لنا
Now you have similar problems, like if you want to identify objects in a photograph.
مسالة اخرى مشابهة   ، اذا اردت تحديد جميع المكونات في صورة
You've got a picture, with maybe with a dog and tree and a cloud and
فمثلا عندك صورة  فيها كلب وشجرة وسحاب
you want the computer to identify what's what.
وتريد من الكمبيوتر ان يساعدك في تحديد وتسمية هذه الاشياء
Then once again, this is a thing that our brains have gotten very good at doing, and
هذه بعض الامثلة التي يستطيع عقلنا حلها بفعالية
we understand what the question is.
فهمنا ماهو السؤال
However, it's hard to really put into words how you identify that this thing's
ولكن من الصعب ان تصف بكلمات كيف تحدد اذا هذا الشيء
a dog and this thing's a tree.
كلب او شجرة
And this sort of business makes it very difficult to teach
من الصعب ان تشرح للكمبيوتر
a computer to do the same thing.
هذا النوع من المسائل ليقوم بحلها
Another thing that you might want to do is teach a computer to play games well like
مسالة اخرى اذا ارادت ان تعلم الكمبيوتر كيف يلعب لعبة
play chess effectively.
مثلا كلعبة الشطرنج
And, once again,
مرة اخرى
this is a thing where we can sort of identify what it means to do this.
هذا شيء نستطيع تحديده وفهمه
But, actually how you want to do it,
ولكن كيف تستطيع عمله
there's a lot of sort of very vague, intuitive things that go on there.
هناك كثير من الاشياء الغامضة
It's not a clearly defined problem that you're trying to solve.
هذه مشكلة غير معرفة بوضوح ونريد حلها
And so, for all of these problems sort of the difficulty is not so
ولكل هذه المسائل / الصعوبة ليست في
much that it's hard to do things quickly.
كيفية حلها بسرعة
But it's hard to even state what it is that you're trying to do and
ولكن الصعوبة تكمن في ماهية الحل وكيف تستطيع ان تفعله
figure out how to approach it.
ومحاولة معرفة كيف تبدأ
Now, these are problems that we're not going to really cover in this class,
لن نتعرض في هذه المادة لهذا النوع من المسائل او المشاكل
we're going to focus on algorithms, how to do things quickly and efficiently.
سنركز تفكيرنا على الخوارزميات وكيف نستطيع تنفيذها بسرعة وفعالية
But if you do want to get into AI and want to try and solve these problems,
اذا اردت ان تجرب ان تحل مشاكل الذكاء الاصطناعي
it will be very important that you have a solid grounding in algorithms, so
فسيكون من المفيد ان تملك قاعدة قوية في فهم الخوارزميات
that once you have some idea of what does it mean to identify
سيكون عندك فكرة  عن معنى
trees in pictures, you will have an idea of what sort of algorithms
تحديد شجرة في صورة  ،  ستكون فكرة عن اي خوارزمية
can actually support these ideas, which sort of ideas you can actually implement
ممكن تساهم في حل هذه الفكرة
in a reasonable amount of time.
ستكون فكرة عن نوع الحلول التي ممكن ان تطبقها في وقت معقول
And so, what we're going to focus on in this course are the algorithms problems.
وايضا سنركز  على مشاكل الخوارزميات
So, we want problems that are cleanly formulated,
ولذلك نحتاج الى مشاكل  معرفة بوضوح
like clear mathematical problems.
مثل مسائل الرياضيات
And some of the things we looked at maybe aren't immediately clear,
وبعض المسائل التي تطرقنا اليها سابقا ،  مثل
like if you want to find the shortest route between two points on a map,
مسائل ايجاد اقصر طري او ايجاد الخط بين نقطتين في خريطة هذه مسائل غير واضحة
that's not immediately a math problem.
وليست مسائل رياضية مباشرة
But, pretty quickly you can interpret it as such.
ولكن بسهولة تستطيع تحويلها الى مسالة رياضيات
You can say, well, I want some sequence of intersections,
فممكن ان تذكر انك تريد متسلسلة من التقاطعات
I'm traveling between such that each pair is connected by a road, and
التي سأسافر خلالها من حيث ان. كل هذه التقاطعات مربوطة بطريق
the sum of the lengths of the roads is as small as possible.
بحيث ان مجموع أطوال هذه الطرق يكون اصغر شيء ممكن
And so, pretty quickly this just becomes a problem where we can very clearly state
وهذه اصبحت مسالة  نستطيع من خلالها
what it is that we're trying to do
تحديد مانود عمله
but, for which it is still nontrivial to solve it.
ولكن تظل مسالة حلها غير بسيط ولا مباشر
And so, that's the sort of thing we're going to be talking about in this class.
هذا النوع من المسائل سوف نتطرق اليه في هذه المادة
And, hopefully,
وان شاء الله
by the end of it you will have a good idea of how to solve these problems,
خلال نهاية المادة سوف تكون فكرة عن كيف حل هذه المسائل
how to write programs that will solve them very quickly and very efficiently.
وكيف تكتب برنامجا لحلها
And that's what we'll be talking about.
وهذا ماسنتحدث عن
I hope you enjoy the rest of the class.
اتمنى ان تستمتعوا ببقية المادة